<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" version="2.0">
    <channel>
      <title>William Guimont-Martin - Android</title>
      <link>https://willguimont.com/</link>
      <description>William Guimont-Martin&#x27;s personal website</description>
      <generator>Zola</generator>
      <language>en</language>
      <atom:link href="https://willguimont.com/tags/android/rss.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
      <lastBuildDate>Wed, 08 Jul 2020 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
      <item>
          <title>FRP: You don&#x27;t own your android phone</title>
          <pubDate>Wed, 08 Jul 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
          <author>William Guimont-Martin</author>
          <link>https://willguimont.com/blog/frp/</link>
          <guid>https://willguimont.com/blog/frp/</guid>
          <description xml:base="https://willguimont.com/blog/frp/">&lt;p&gt;Recently, I had to change my phone. I got my grandfather’s old smartphone to replace it. I wanted to try a new OS to replace Google’s Android, I was thinking of trying either &lt;a class=&quot;external&quot; href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;lineageos.org&#x2F;&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;LineageOS&lt;&#x2F;a&gt; or &lt;a class=&quot;external&quot; href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;resurrectionremix.com&#x2F;&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Ressurection REMIX OS&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;. So, I candidly hard reset it by entering the “Recovery Menu”, just like I would on any computer I ever installed Linux on.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Except, there was something that went wrong. I got a weird error message. So, I booted the phone to see what was going on. I start the setup procedure. I am asked to log in with a Google Account, so I do. There, I get another weird message: I had to log in with the phone’s owner account…&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The phone was locked. Locked by Google. The physical device that I thought I owned, locked by the inside by Google.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That particular “security” is called &lt;a class=&quot;external&quot; href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;www.androidcentral.com&#x2F;factory-reset-protection-what-you-need-know&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Factory Reset Protection&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;. As far as I know, it is impossible to bypass that “protection”. Basically, once activated Google owns &lt;em&gt;your&lt;&#x2F;em&gt; phone.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I lost a lot of time, had to ask my grandfather to enter a code on his new phone to unlock the one he gave me.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When I was finally able to set up the phone, I was greeted by a lot of preinstalled and un-uninstallable applications. Truly, the smartphone &lt;a class=&quot;external&quot; href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;en.wikipedia.org&#x2F;wiki&#x2F;Oligopoly&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;oligopoly&lt;&#x2F;a&gt; is a bad thing for users.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Both Android and iPhone phones are locked, you don’t own your phone like you own your computer.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We need more free and open-source alternatives, just like GNU&#x2F;Linux is in the computer OS market.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
</description>
      </item>
    </channel>
</rss>
